Welcome to Thailand.
أهلاً بكم إلى تايلندا
Now, when I was a young man -- 40 years ago,
عندما كنت شاباً .. منذ اربعين عام مضت
the country was very, very poor
كانت الدولة فقيرة جداً .. جداً
with lots and lots and lots of people living in poverty.
كان هناك الكثير ممن يعشيون في فقر متقع
We decided to do something about it,
وقررنا ان نقوم بشيء حيال ذلك
but we didn't begin with a welfare program
ولكن لم نبدأ بخطط تنمية
or a poverty reduction program.
او خطط حد من الفقر
But we began with a family-planning program,
بل بدأنا من خطة تنظيم النسل .. والاسرة
following a very successful
مما رفع ذلك بصورة ناجحة جداً
maternal child health activity,
مستوى الامومة .. والصحة
sets of activities.
وكل ما يتبع لذلك
So basically, no one would accept family planning
في البداية .. من غير المنطقي ان يوافق احدٌ على مشروع تنظيم النسل
if their children didn't survive.
ان لم يكن يضمن ان يعيش ابنه " الوحيد " حياة طويلة
So the first step: get to the children, get to the mothers,
لذا كانت الخطوة الاولى .. احسن وضع الاطفال .. حسن وضع الامهات
and then follow up with family planning.
ومن ثم ابدأ بمشروع تنظيم النسل
Not just child mortality alone, you need also family planning.
فنحن لا نحتاج فحسب تقليل وفيات الاطفال .. بل نحتاج تنظيم النسل ايضاً
Now let me take you back
دعوني أأخذكم الى الماضي
as to why we needed to do it.
لكي اشرح لكم لماذا كان يتوجب علينا القيام بذلك
In my country, that was the case in 1974.
في بلد كان معدل الانجاب في عام 1974
Seven children per family --
هو سبعة اطفال لكل عائلة
tremendous growth at 3.3 percent.
انه رقم نمو سكاني كبير وصل الى 3.3
There was just no future.
ولم يكن هنالك مستقبل لجميع هؤلاء الاطفال
We needed to reduce the population growth rate.
لذا توجب علينا تقليل نسبة النمو السكاني
So we said, "Let's do it."
وقلنا .. علينا القيام بذلك
The women said, "We agree. We'll use pills,
فقالت النسوة .. نحن موافقات.. دعونا نستخدم حبوب منع الحمل
but we need a doctor to prescribe the pills,"
ولكن لكي تسخدمها .. يجب ان يصفها لك طبيب
and we had very, very few doctors.
وكنا نملك عدداً قليلاً جدا من الاطباء
We didn't take no as an answer;
نحن لا نقبل بكلمة " لا " كجواب لطلبنا
we took no as a question.
بل كسؤال
We went to the nurses and the midwives, who were also women,
لقد ذهبنا الى الممرضات والقابلات .. والتي كن نسوة حتماً ..
and did a fantastic job
وقمنا بعمل رائع معهم
at explaining how to use the pill.
وشرحنا لهم كيفية استخدام حبوب منع الحمل تلك
That was wonderful,
وكان هذا رائعا ً
but it covered only 20 percent of the country.
ولكننا لم نستطع الا ان نغطي 20% من الدولة
What do we do for the other 80 percent --
وال80% الباقون لم نصل اليهم
leave them alone and say, "Well, they're not medical personnel."
لانهم لم يكونوا محتكون مع اطباء او ممرضات او نحو ذلك
No, we decided to do a bit more.
لذا قررنا ان نقوم بشيء اكبر
So we went to the ordinary people that you saw.
لقد ذهبنا الى الاشخاص العادين
Actually, below that yellow sign --
في الحقيقة اسفل تلك العلامة الصفراء
I wish they hadn't wiped that,
كنت اتمنى لو انهم لم يزيلوها ..
because there was "Coca-Cola" there.
هنالك كان علب كوكا كولا ..
We were so much bigger than Coca-Cola in those days.
لقد كنا نوزع بمنحى اكبر من شركة كوكا كولا في تلك الايام
And no difference,
ولا يوجد فرق بيننا وبينهم
the people they chose were the people we chose.
كان الاشخاص الذين تختارهم الشركة .. هم نفسهم الذين نختارهم نحن ايضاً
They were well-known in the community,
فهم اشخاص معروفون في مجتمعهم
they knew that customers were always right,
وهم يعرفون الزبائن جيداً .. ولديهم قاعدة الزبون دوما على حق
and they were terrific, and they practiced their family planning themselves.
وكانوا رائعين جداً .. وقد طبقوا تنظيم النسل على انفسهم ايضاً
So they could supply pills and condoms
ولقد قدموا حبوب منع الحمل .. والواقيات الذكرية للعامة
throughout the country, in every village of the country.
عبر الدولة .. في كل قريبة .. وفي كل ناحية من تايلندا
So there we are. We went to the people
ها نحن هنا .. لقد استخدمنا العامة
who were seen as the cause of the problem
الذين كان يلقى على عاتقهم حدوث هذه المشكلة
to be the solution.
فأصبحوا الآن جزءاً من الحل
Wherever there were people --
واينما وجد الناس ..
and you can see boats with the women, selling things --
سوف ترى قوارب .. مع نسوة .. تبيع هذه الاشياء
here's the floating market
هنا نرى قارب عائم
selling bananas and crabs
يبيع الموز والخضار
and also contraceptives --
ويبيع موانع الحمل ايضاً
wherever you find people,
اينما يوجد الناس ..
you'll find contraceptives in Thailand.
سيوجد وسائل منع حمل في تايلندا
And then we decided, why not get to religion
ومن ثم قررنا ان نلجأ للدين
because in the Philippines,
لانه في الفلبين
the Catholic Church was pretty strong,
الكنسية الكاثوليكية كانت قوية جداً
and Thai people were Buddhist.
وفي تايلندا .. هم بوذيون
We went to them and they said, "Look, could you help us?"
لقد ذهبنا اليهم وطلبنا منهم مساعدتنا
I'm there -- the one in blue, not the yellow --
وانا في هذه الصورة ارتدي الازرق .. لا الاصفر
holding a bowl of holy water
احمل وعاءاً فيه ماءً مقدساً
for the monk to sprinkle holy water
للناسك .. لكي يقوم برش ذلك الماء
on pills and condoms
على حبوب منع الحمل والواقيات الذكرية
for the sanctity of the family.
من اجل صحة الاسر
And this picture was sent throughout the country.
وقد تم ارسال تلك الصورة عبر البلاد كلها
So some of the monks in the villages were doing the same thing themselves.
ومن ثم قام نساك .. القرى بالقيام بالامر ذاته
And the women were saying, "No wonder we have no side-effects.
وقالت النسوة في أنفسهن .. لا عجب لا يوجد تأثيرات جانبية لتلك الحبوب ..
It's been blessed."
لان النساك قد باركوها
That was their perception.
لقد كان هذا منظورهم للامور
And then we went to teachers.
ومن ثم لجأنا للمدرسين
You need everybody to be involved
كنا نريد ان يشارك معنا الجميع
in trying to provide whatever it is
لكي نؤمن ما يتطلبه الامر
that make humanity a better place.
لكي نحول البلد الى مكان يمكن العيش فيه بصورة افضل
So we went to the teachers.
لذا لجأنا الى المدرسين
Over a quarter of a million were taught about family planning
مما ادى الى تعليم اكثر من ربع مليون مدرس عن كيفية تنظيم النسل
with a new alphabet -- A, B for birth, C for condom,
حيث كانت ت = التوليد و و= الواقي الذكري
I for IUD, V for vasectomy.
ل = اللولب , ق = ربط القناة الدافقة
And then we had a snakes and ladders game, where you throw dice.
ومن ثم قمنا بصناعة لعبة " السلم والثعبان " حيث كان الاطفال يرمون النرد
If you land on anything pro-family planning, you move ahead.
وان تحركت القطعة على نقطة " تنظيم نسل " يتقدم اللاعب الى الامام
Like, "Mother takes the pill every night.
مثل " الامهات تأخذ الحبوب كل مساء ..
Very good, mother. Move ahead.
جيد . جداً .. والدتي .. تقدمي الى الامام ..
Uncle buys a condom. Very good, uncle. Move ahead.
الرجال يشترون الواقي الذكري .. جيد جداً عمي .. تقدم الى الامام
Uncle gets drunk, doesn't use condom. Come back, start again."
الرجل قد شرب الخمرة .. ولم يشتري الواقي الذكري .. عليك بالرجوع الى الخلف !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Again, education, class entertainment.
مرة اخرى .. التعليم .. والتعليم بالالعاب
And the kids were doing it in school too.
والاطفال كانوا يتعلمون في المدارس ..
We had relay races with condoms,
لقد كنا ننظم سباقات بالواقيات الذكرية
we had children's condom-blowing championship.
وكان لدينا مسابقة نفخ الواقيات الذكرية
And before long,
وما هي الا فترة وجيزة حتى عرف
the condom was know as the girl's best friend.
الواقي الذكري وانه الصديق الامثل للفتاة
In Thailand, for poor people, diamonds don't make it --
في تايلندا .. الفقراء لا يستطيعون شراء الالماس ..
so the condom is the girl's best friend.
لذا فالواقي الذكري هو الصديق الامثل للفتاة
We introduced our first microcredit program in 1975,
لقد قدمنا اول برنامج للقروض الصغيرة في عام 1975
and the women who organized it said,
وكانت النسوة التي تنظم الامر تقول
"We only want to lend
سوف نقرضك فحسب ..
to women who practice family planning.
ان كنت تطبقين تنظيم النسل ..
If you're pregnant, take care of your pregnancy.
ان كانت حاملاً .. اذهبي واعتني بحملك
If you're not pregnant, you can take a loan out from us."
ان لم تكوني حاملاً .. تعالي لكي نقرضك
And that was run by them.
وقد تم ادارة ذلك من قبلهن
And after 35/36 years,
وبعد 35\36 عام
it's still going on.
مازال ذلك الامر يسير على قدمٍ وثاق
It's a part of the Village Development Bank;
انه جزء من بنك تنمية القرى
it's not a real bank, but it's a fund -- microcredit.
انه ليس بنك حقيقي .. انه بنك تقديم قروض صغيرة
And we didn't need a big organization to run it --
اي اننا لا نحتاج الى مؤسسة كبيرة لادارته
it was run by the villagers themselves.
انه يدار من قبل القرويين انفسهم
And you probably hardly see a Thai man there,
وكما تلاحظون انتم لا ترون الرجال ابداً
it's always women, women, women, women.
ان النسوة دوما هن في الصور .. النسوة والنسوة
And then we thought we'd help America,
ومن ثم قلنا لانفسنا .. ربما يتوجب علينا مساعدة امريكا
because America's been helping everyone,
لان امريكا كانت تساعد الجميع
whether they want help or not.
سواء كانوا يريدون المساعدة او لا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this is on the Fourth of July.
وهذه الصورة في الرابع من يوليو/ تموز
We decided to provide vasectomy to all men,
قررنا ان نقوم بقطع القناة الدافقة لكل الرجال
but in particular, American men to the front of the queue,
ولكن ركزنا على الامريكين الذين يقفون في الصف
right up to the Ambassador's residence
بالقرب من منزل السفير الامريكي
during his vin d'honneur.
اثناء جولته
And the hotel gave us the ballroom for it --
وقد اعطانا الفندق قاعة الرقص للقيام بذلك ..
very appropriate room.
غرفةٌ لائقة جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And since it was near lunch time,
وعندما اقترب موعد الغداء
they said, "All right, we'll give you some lunch.
قلنا لهم سوف نقدم لكم الغداء
Of course, it must be American cola.
طبعاً كان يجب ان يكون امريكياً
You get two brands, Coke and Pepsi.
وكان لدينا كوكا كولا .. وببسي
And then the food is either hamburger or hotdog."
والطعام كان اما همبرغر او نقانق
And I thought a hotdog will be more symbolic.
رغم ان النقانق تبدو اكثر ملائمة للحملة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And here is this, then, young man called Willy Bohm
ومن ثم هذا هو ويلي بوهم
who worked for the USAID.
وكان يعمل في برنامج المساعدات الامريكية
Obviously, he's had his vasectomy
ويبدو انه يتم قطع قناته الدافقة
because his hotdog is half eaten, and he was very happy.
لان النقانق التي بيده قد أُكل منها .. وهو يبدو سعيدٌ جداً
It made a lot of news in America, and it angered some people also.
لقد انتشر صدى هذا الحدث كثيراً في امريكاً .. وقد اعترض كثيرون عليه ايضاً
I said, "Don't worry. Come over and I'll do the whole lot of you."
فقتل لهم .. لا تقلقوا .. تعالوا الى تايلندا .. وسوف نقدم لكم الكثير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what happened?
مالذي حدث لاحقاً
In all this thing,
تبعاً لكل تلك الامور
from seven children to 1.5 children,
لقد انخفض الانجاب من 7 اطفال الى 1.5
population growth rate of 3.3 to 0.5.
والنمو السكاني من 3.3 الى 0.5
You could call it the Coca-Cola approach if you like --
يمكننا ان نسمي تلك الطريقة طريقة كوكا كولا .. ان احببتم
it was exactly the same thing.
لقد كنا نتبع نفس الطريقة
I'm not sure whether Coca-Cola followed us, or we followed Coca-Cola,
لا ادري ان كنا قد اتبعنا كوكا كولا . .او ان كوكا كولا اتبعتنا
but we're good friends.
ولكننا كنا نسير معاً كاصدقاء
And so that's the case of everyone joining in.
وكانت هذه الطريقة التي دمجنا فيها الجميع
We didn't have a strong government. We didn't have lots of doctors.
لم نكن نملك حكومة قوية .. ولم نكن نملك العديد من الاطباء
But it's everybody's job
ولكن تلك المهمة كانت مهمة الجميع
who can change attitude and behavior.
التي غيرت تصرف وانطباع الجميع في الدولة
Then AIDS came along and hit Thailand,
ومن ثم ضربنا مرض الايدز
and we had to stop doing a lot of good things
واضطررنا لا نوقف القيام بعدة امور جيدة
to fight AIDS.
لكي نحارب الايدز
But unfortunately, the government was in denial, denial, denial.
وللاسف كانت حكومتنا في موقع انكار .. وانكار .. وانكار
So our work wasn't affected.
لذا لم يكن عملنا يؤتي ثمره
So I thought, "Well, if you can't go to the government, go to the military."
فقلت لنفسي .. ان لم استطع الاستفادة من الحكومة .. لا بدو ان ألجأ الى الجيش
So I went to the military
لذا ذهبت الى الجيش
and asked to borrow 300 radio stations.
وطلبت منهم استعارة 300 محطة اذاعية
They have more than the government,
انها اكثر مما تملكه الدولة
and they've got more guns than the government.
ولديهم اسحلة ايضاً اكثر من الدولة !
So I asked them, could they help us
فطلبت منهم المساعدة
in our fight against HIV.
في حربنا ضد فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة
And after I gave them statistics,
وبعد ان اعطيتهم بعضاً من الاحصائيات
they said, "Yes. Okay. You can use all the radio stations, television stations."
وافقوا على اعارتنا جميع محطات الراديو والتلفاز
And that's when we went onto the airwaves.
ومن ثم اصبحت توعيتنا تنتشر في الاثير
And then we got a new prime minister soon after that.
ومن ثم تم تعين رئيس وزراء جديد
And he said, "Mechai, could you come and join?"
وقال لي .. ميشاي .. هلا عملنا سويةً
He asked me in because he liked my wife a lot.
لقد طلب مني ذلك لانه معجبٌ بأنشطة زوجتي
So I said, "Okay."
فقلت " نعم "
He became the chairman of the National AIDS Committee
وقد اصبح عضو مجلس في لجنة محاربة الايدز القومية
and increased the budget fifty-fold.
مما زاد ميزانيتنا الى الضعف
Every ministry, even judges, had to be involved in AIDS education --
وغدا كل وزير .. وكل قاض .. منخرط في عملية التوعية بخصوص الايدز
everyone -- and we said the public, institutions,
وكل شخص من العامة .. وفي المؤسسات
religious institutions, schools --
والمؤسسات الدينية .. والمدارس
everyone was involved.
الجميع كان يتوجب عليه المشاركة
And here, every media person
بالاضافة الى رجال الاعلام
had to be trained for HIV.
كان يتوجب عليهم التدرب من اجل التوعية ضد فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة
And we gave every station half a minute extra
وقد اعطينا كل محطة نصف دقيقة اكثر
for advertising to earn more money.
للاعلان .. لكي يحصلوا على اموال اكثر
So they were happy with that.
وكانوا سعداء بذلك
And then AIDS education in all schools,
ومن ثم انتقلت التوعية ضد الايدز الى المدارس
starting from university.
بدءاً من الجامعات
And these are high school kids teaching high school kids.
وهنا طلاب مدارس الثانوية .. يقومون بتعليم طلاب مدارسهم الثانوية
And the best teachers were the girls, not the boys,
وكان المعلمون الافضل من الاناث .. ليس الذكور
and they were terrific.
وكان الامر رائعاً
And these girls who go around teaching about safe sex and HIV
وكانت الاناث .. تنشرن الوعي عن ممارسة الجنس الصحيحة .. وكيفية تلافي فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة
were known as Mother Theresa.
وكن يعرفن باسم " الام تيريزا "
And then we went down one more step.
ومن ثم قررنا توسيع القاعدة
These are primary school kids -- third, fourth grade --
وقررنا استهداف المدارس الابتدائية .. الصف الثالث والرابع
going to every household in the village,
فذهبنا الى دور التعليم في القرى
every household in the whole of Thailand,
وفي كل ناحية في تايلندا
giving AIDS information and a condom
واعطينا معلومات عن مرض الايدز والواقيات الذكرية
to every household,
لكل منزل
given by these young kids.
بواسطة هؤلاء الاطفال
And no parents objected, because we were trying to save lives,
ولم يكن يعترض اي والد على ذلك .. لاننا كنا نحاول انقاذ حياتهم
and this was a lifesaver.
وكان هذا هو طوق النجاة
And we said, "Everyone needs to be involved."
وكما قلت " يجب ان ينخرط الجميع بذلك "
So you have the companies also realizing
ولقد ادركت الشركات ايضاً هذا
that sick staff don't work, and dead customers don't buy.
فالمنتجات المكدسة .. لا تفيد .. والزبائن الذين يموتون لا يشترون
So they all trained.
لذا تم تدريبهم ايضاً
And then we have this Captain Condom,
وقمنا باختراع شخصية " الكابتن واقي ذكري "
with his Harvard MBA,
وبالمناسبة هو يحمل ماجستير من هارفرد
going to schools and night spots.
وكان يذهب الى المدارس .. والنوادي الليلية
And they loved him. You need a symbol of something.
وقد احبه الناس .. تعلمون ان لكل حملة او برنامج او دولة يجب
In every country, every program, you need a symbol,
ان يكون هنالك رمزاً .. وقد كان هو رمز حملتنا وبرنامجنا
and this is probably the best thing he's ever done with his MBA.
وربما كان هذا افضل شيء قام به بدرجة الماجستير تلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then we gave condoms out everywhere on the streets --
ومن ثم قمنا بتوزيع الواقيات الذكرية في كل مكان
everywhere, everywhere.
في كل مكان
In taxis, you get condoms.
في سيارات الاجرة .. كنت تحصل على واقٍ ذكري
And also, in traffic,
وفي المواصلات العامة
the policemen give you condoms -- our "cops and rubbers" programs.
وكان رجال الشرطة يوزعونه ايضاً .. في برنامج الشرطة والشعب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, can you imagine New York policemen giving out condoms?
هل يمكنك تخيل رجل شرطة من نيويورك يوزع الواقيات الذكرية ..
Of course I can. And they'd enjoy it immensely;
نعم انا استطيع .. وسوف يستمتعون بذلك جداً
I see them standing around right now, everywhere.
انا اتخيلهم الان .. في كل مكان
Imagine if they had condoms,
تخيلوا .. انهم يملكون الواقيات الذكرية
giving out to all sorts of people.
وانهم يعطونها للمارة
And then, new change,
ومن ثم قمنا بعدة تغيرات
we had hair bands, clothing
قمنا بعمل قبعات .. وملابس ..
and the condom for your mobile phone
وقدمنا واقي ذكري لهاتفك المحمول
during the rainy season.
لحمايته اثناء الجو الممطر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And these were the condoms that we introduced.
هذه هي الواقيات الذكرية التي نُنتج
One says, "Weapon of mass protection."
واحد منها مكتوب عليه " سلاح الانتاج الشامل "
We found --
لقد وجدناه ..
you know -- somebody here was searching for the weapon of mass destruction,
لقد كان هناك من يبحث عن اسلحة الدمار الشامل
but we have found the weapon of mass protection: the condom.
ولكننا وجدنا اسلحة الانتاج الشامل .. انها الواقيات الذكرية
And then it says here, with the American flag,
وهنا واحد منها يحمل علماً امريكيا
"Don't leave home without it."
ومكتوب عليه لا تترك البيت من غير واقٍ ذكري
But I have some to give out afterward.
ولكن علي ان احذركم
But let me warn you, these are Thai-sized,
ان واقياتنا الذكري بأحجام تايلندية !
so be very careful.
لذا خذوا حذركم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so you can see
وهنا كما ترون
that condoms can do so many things.
يمكننا ان نروج للواقيات الذكرية بعدة طرق
Look at this --
مثل هذه
I gave this to Al Gore and to Bill Senior also.
لقد اعطيتها لآل غور .. ول بيل سينير أيضاً
Stop global warming; use condoms.
ان اردت ان توقف الاحتباس الحراري .. استخدم الواقي الذكري
And then this is the picture I mentioned to you --
وهذه الصورة التي ذكرت من قبل ..
the weapon of mass protection.
سلاح الانتاج الشامل
And let the next Olympics save some lives.
ولنجعل الالومبياد القادمة تنقذ بعض الارواح
Why just run around?
ولماذا ندور في حلبات السباق فحسب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then finally,
وختاماً
in Thailand we're Buddhist, we don't have a God,
في تايلندا نحن بوذيون .. ولا نؤمن بوجود اله ..
so instead, we say, "In rubber we trust."
لذا بدلاً عن ذلك .. نقول " في المطاط نحن نثق "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So you can see that we added everything to our endeavor
يمكنكم ان تروا كيف دمجنا كل شيء بخطتنا
to make life better for the people.
لكي نحسن من معيشة الاشخاص
We had condoms in all the refrigerators in the hotels and the schools,
لقد وضعنا الواقيات الذكرية في الثلاجات في الفنادق وفي المدارس
because alcohol impairs judgment.
لان الكحول تؤثر على الحكم
And then what happened?
ومن ثم مالذي حدث ..
After all this time, everybody joined in.
بعد كل هذا اندمج المجتمع كله في هذه الحملة
According to the U.N.,
وتبعاً للامم المتحدة
new cases of HIV
فان وضع فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة
declined by 90 percent,
انخفض الى 90% !!
and according to the World Bank,
وتبعاً للبنك الدولي
7.7 million lives were saved.
فان 7.7 مليون شخص تم انقاذ حياته
Otherwise there wouldn't be many Thais walking around today.
ولولا هذا .. لما كان هنالك الكثير من التايلنديين يسيرون هنا
So it just showed you, you could do something about it.
وهذا يريكم كيف انه يمكن القيام بشيء
90 percent of the funding came from Thailand.
رغم ان 90% من التمويل كان من داخل تايلندا
There was political commitment, some financial commitment,
ولكن كان هنالك التزام سياسي .. وقليل من الالتزام الاقتصادي
and everybody joined in the fight.
والجميع شارك في هذه الحرب
So just don't leave it to the specialists and doctors and nurses.
لذا لا تتركوا هذه الامور للاختصاصيين .. ولا للاطباء .. ولا للممرضات
We all need to help.
الجميع عليه ان يساعد
And then we decided to help people out of poverty,
ومن ثم قررنا ان نساعد الناس للخروج من الفقر
now that we got AIDS somewhat out of the way --
بعد ان حيدنا مرض الايدز بعيداً
this time, not with government alone,
هذه المرة .. لم نعمل مع الحكومة فحسب
but in cooperation with the business community.
ولكن مع الشركات .. ومع المجتمع الاقتصادي
Because poor people are business people
لان الفقراء .. هم اقتصاديون ..
who lack business skills and access to credit.
ولكن يفتقرون الى مهارات والتمويل الكافي
Those are the things to be provided by the business community.
وهذه الامور يتم توفيرها من خلال المجتمع الاقتصادي
We're trying to turn them into barefoot entrepreneurs,
ونحن نحاول ان نحول الفقراء .. الى ما ندعوه "عصاميون حفاة اقدام "
little business people.
اي رجال اعمال صغار
The only way out of poverty is through business enterprise.
والطريقة الوحيدة للخروج من الفقر .. هي تعليم العصامية الاقتصادية
So, that was done.
وقد قمنا بعمل ذلك
The money goes from the company into the village
لقد نقلنا التمويل من الشركات الى القُرى
via tree-planting.
عبر زراعة الاشجار
It's not a free gift.
ان الاموال لم تكن تقدم هكذا ..
They plant the trees, and the money goes into their microcredit fund,
لقد كانت الاشجار تزرع .. ونتاجها يذهب الى برنامج القروض الصغيرة
which we call the Village Development Bank.
والذي ندعوه بنك التنمية القروي
Everybody joins in,
والجميع شارك بهذا
and they feel they own the bank,
والجميع شعر انه يملك البنك
because they have brought the money in.
لانه ساهموا في مدخولاته
And before you can borrow the money, you need to be trained.
وقبل ان تستعير المال منه .. يجب عليك ان تتدرب
And we believe if you want to help the poor,
ونحن نؤمن .. ان لمساعدة الفقراء
those who are living in poverty,
والذين يعيشون في الفقر
access to credit must be a human right.
عليك تامين التمويل لهم .. والذي يجب ان يكون حقاً انسانيا
Access to credit must be a human right.
ان الحصول على التمويل حقٌ انساني
Otherwise they'll never get out of poverty.
والا فان احداً لن يخرج من دائرة الفقر
And then before getting a loan, you must be trained.
اذا .. قبل ان تحصل على قرضك يجب ان يتم تدريبك
Here's what we call a "barefoot MBA,"
وهذا ما ندعوه ماجستير حفاة الاقدام
teaching people how to do business
وهو لتعليم الناس كيفية ادارة مشاريعهم
so that, when they borrow money, they'll succeed with the business.
لكي ينجحوا عندما يقترضون المال
These are some of the businesses:
وهذه بعضٌ من المشاريع التي قاموا بها
mushrooms, crabs, vegetables,
بين الفطر.. الخضار .. البقول
trees, fruits,
الاشجار .. الفواكه
and this is very interesting -- Nike ice cream and Nike biscuits;
وهذا مثيرٌ جدا .. بسكويت وآيس كريم بعلامة " نايك "
this is a village sponsored by Nike.
ان هذه القرية تحت رعاية شركة " نايك "
They said, "They should stop making shoes and clothes.
لقد قالوا .. علينا ان نتوقف عن صناعة الاحذية والملابس
Make these better, because we can afford them."
لنصنع هذه .. لان الناس يمكنها شرائها
And then we have silk, Thai silk.
ولدينا الحرير .. الحرير التايلندي
Now we're making Scottish tartans, as you can see on the left,
ونحن الان نصنع الترتان السكوتلندي الذي يمكن رؤيته على اليسار
to sell to all people of Scottish ancestors.
وقوم ببيعه لكبار السن الاسكوتلندين
So anyone sitting in and watching TV,
واي احد يشاهدني
get in touch with me.
يمكنه التواصل معي بخصوص ذلك
And then this is our answer to Starbucks in Thailand --
وهذا هو اصدارنا من ستاربكس في تايلندا
"Coffee and Condoms."
القهوة والواقي الذكري
See, Starbucks you awake, we keep you awake and alive.
ان ستاربكس تبقيك يقظاً بكافينها .. ولكن نحن نبقيك متيقظاً وعلى قيد الحياة
That's the difference.
هذا هو الفرق
Can you imagine, at every Starbucks
تخيلوا .. في كل فرع من ستاربكس
that you can also get condoms?
يمكنك ان تحصل على واقٍ ذكري
You can order your condoms with your with your cappuccino.
يمكنك ان تطلب الواقي الذكري مع كوب الكابتشينو خاصتك
And then now, finally in education,
ومن ثم في التعليم
we want to change the school as being underutilized
اردنا ان نحول المدارس الغير مستغلة
into a place where it's a lifelong learning center for everyone.
الى مكان يمكنه ان يعلم الحياة الطويلة لكل الاشخاص
We call this our School-Based Integrated Rural Development.
نحن نسمي هذه المدرسة مدرسة التنمية الريفية المتكاملة
And it's a center, a focal point
وهي مركز حيوي
for economic and social development.
للتنمية الاجتماعية والاقتصادية
Re-do the school,
اعيدوا صناعة مدارسكم
make it serve the community needs.
لكي تخدم مجتمعاتكم
And here is a bamboo building --
وهنا مبنى من الخيزران
all of them are bamboo.
كل شيء هنا من الخيزران
This is a geodesic dome made of bamboo.
وهذه القبة الجيوديزية مصنوعة من الخيزران
And I'm sure Buckminster Fuller would be very, very proud
وانا متاكد ان بامينستر فولير سوف يكون فخورا بها
to see a bamboo geodesic dome.
عندما يرى هذه القبة الخيزرانية
And we use vegetables around the school ground,
ونحن نستخدم الخضار التي تزرع في الاراضي المجاورة للمدارس
so they raise their own vegetables.
حيث كل مدرسة تزرع خضارها الخاصة بها
And then, finally, I firmly believe,
ومن ثم وانا أُؤمن بشدة
if we want the MDGs to work --
انه ان اردنا ان نحقق
the Millennium Development Goals --
الاهداف الألفية للتنمية
we need to add family planning to it.
نحن نحتاج ان ندرج تنظيم النسل ضمنها
Of course, child mortality first and then family planning --
ولكن حتماً خفض معدل وفيات الاطفال أولا ومن ثم تنظيم النسل
everyone needs family planning service --
والجميع يجب ان يكون على دراية بتلك الامور
it's underutilized.
لانها مقاربة ناجحة غير مستغلة
So we have now found the weapon of mass protection.
وها نحن قد وجدنا سلاح الانتاج الشامل
And we also ask the next Olympics
وسوف نطلب من الالومبياد القادمة
to be involved in saving lives.
ان تشاركنا في انقاذ الارواح
And then, finally, that is our network.
وهذا هو موقعنا الالكتروني وشبكتنا
And these are our Thai tulips.
وهذه هي ازهار التوليب الخاصة بتايلندا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much indeed.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
( تصفيق )